Guide to the Pittsburgh Stamp Company Records, 1914-1998 AIS.2011.05
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pittsburgh Stamp Company Records
1914-1998
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pittsburgh Stamp Company
AIS.2011.05
2.55 Linear Feet (4 manuscript boxes)
The Pittsburgh Stamp Company Records contain administrative records, company correspondence, promotional materials, schematic drawings and photographs of company products, employees, tools, and machinery.
Access Restrictions
Shareholders, Dividends and Distributions Forms, 1997-1998 is restricted until 2070, 72 years after the records' creation.
Previous Citation
Pittsburgh Stamp Company Records, 1914-1998, AIS.2011.05, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
James H. Matthews and Company Records, 1864-1961, AIS.1965.17, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following three series:
Series I. Records
Series II. Photographs
Series III. Artifacts
Scope and Content Notes
The Pittsburgh Stamp Company Records contain administrative records, company correspondence, promotional materials, schematic drawings and photographs of company products, employees, tools, and machinery. The photographs exist in a variety of formats including print paper, instant film, and photographic paper. The artifacts include the corporate seal and stamp/die.
History
The Pittsburgh Stamp Company was founded in 1912 as the Holland Brass Company in McKees Rocks, Pa, by James F. Greene, Joseph P. Huhn, and N. R. Roach. It was incorporated in 1914 by the State of Pennsylvania. In 1915 the name of the company was legally changed to The Pittsburgh Steel Stamp Company. Then in 1920 the company name was changed to The Pittsburgh Stamp Company. Between 1915 and 1920 leadership changed, although it appears that co-founder James F. Greene remained associated with the company. Also in 1920, the company issued new stock. The new shareholders, as listed in 1920, were John Nagy, Frank Weber, Otto Hess, W. F. A. Schafer, Herman A. Weber, C. W. Elton, William A. McCarlin, H .D. Marlin, and Charles V. Mack. Subsequent correspondence and shareholders lists document changes in company ownership and leadership.
The company moved from McKees Rocks to the North Side of Pittsburgh circa 1920 and was located at 811 South Canal Street. In 1975 the company purchased property on South Side Avenue in what is the now the Spring Hill neighborhood of Pittsburgh. The company remained at this location until it was bought by Matthews International Corporation in 1998. The sale was proposed in 1997 and involved a legal dispute between Pittsburgh Stamp Company and Matthews that was settled in 1998.
The Pittsburgh Stamp Company produced metal plaques for retail storefronts, funeral homes, memorials, and financial institutions across the United States. Clients also included large corporations such as Texaco, Heinz, and Kellogg's.
Factories -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Factories -- Pennsylvania -- McKees Rocks; Plaques, plaquettes; Stock certificates; Business records; Metal trade -- Pennsylvania -- McKees Rocks; Metal trade -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Metal stamping; McKees Rocks (Pa.); Business and Industry; North Side (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Labor; Manufacturing industries -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Manufacturing industries -- Pennsylvania -- McKees Rocks; Photographs; Pittsburgh Steel Stamp Company; Holland Brass Company; Pittsburgh Stamp Company
- Records, 1914-1998; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains the records of the company, which include by-laws, charter documents, drawings, correspondence, lease agreements, deeds of property, documents relating to the company's sale to Matthews International Corporation, and records relating to the stockholders.
  - By-laws, 1970-1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Charter, 1914-1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Deeds for 1121 South Side Avenue, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Directors' Meetings, 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Drawings, Schematics for Tools, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Drawings, Promotional Illustrations, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Insurance Policy, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lease Agreements for 811-815 South Canal Street, 1921-1929 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Matthews International Corporation, Sale of Company, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Matthews International Corporation, Settlement, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Promissory Notes, 1956-1986 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Recommendations, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Resignations, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Shareholders, Correspondence, 1971-1998 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Shareholders, Dividends and Distribution Forms [Restricted], 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Shareholders, Lists of Names, circa 1920-1991 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Shareholders, Meetings, circa 1979-1991 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Stock Certificates, 1920-1962 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Stock Certificates, 1962-1973 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Stock Certificates, 1991-1995 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Stock Certificates (loose), 1971-1995 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Suppliers and other Companies, Ads and Catalogs, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Photographs, II.
  This series contains photographs that depict employees at work, machinery, tools, and work samples.
  - Employees and Machinery, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Plaques, Financial Institutions, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Plaques, Funeral Homes, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Plaques, Memorials and Dedications, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Plaques, Other Businesses, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Plaques, Retail Stores, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Layout Photos, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Stamps, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Tools (color--instant film images), undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Tools, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Artifacts, III.
  This series contains a metal stamp/die with the company name and the logo for its "Thor" brand. It also contains the corporate seal which was used to authenticate company shares and other offical documents.
  - Corporate Seal, undated (Box 4)
  - Metal Stamp/Die, undated